<?xml version="1.0"?>
<release-notes>
  <release version="1.2.3_01" debug="beta" date="20110831T160000">
    <item type="fix">Fixed bug in updater</item>
  </release>
  <release version="1.2.3" debug="beta" date="20110830T190000">
    <note>Linux and Windows users, please go to http://spato.net/download and install this update manually.</note>
    <item type="new">Screenshot feature can now save PDF, PNG and export the current node layout
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">Press <b>S</b> to bring up the screenshot settings window,
        which is also accessible via the context menu of the network drop-down (in the upper-left corner).</div></item>
    <item type="enh">Better system integration on Windows and Linux</item>
    <item type="enh">Improved update mechanism and faster application startup</item>
    <item type="fix">Various minor bug fixes</item>
    <item type="enh">Source code ported from Processing to pure Java
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">SPaTo still uses the awesome Processing libraries but can now
        be built from the sources without the Processing Development Environment.  Also, the cross-platform tool
        Apache Ant is now used as the build system (instead of <tt>make</tt>).</div></item>
  </release>
  <release version="1.2.2" debug="beta" date="20110604T220000">
    <note>Assuming that no immediate bug-fixes are necessary, this will become the public release version.</note>
    <item type="new">Now available for the Linux platform</item>
    <item type="new">Added option to show the full network or the immediate next neighbors of a node
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">The buttons to toggle these options are currently
        invisible since the full network option may make the application irresponsibly unresponsive.
        <ul>
          <li><b>F</b> toggles display of the full network</li>
          <li><b>E</b> toggles display of the immediate neighbors of the current root node</li>
          <li><b>L</b> toggles superimposed display of the shortest-path tree</li>
          <li>Holding down <b>Alt</b> while displaying immediate neighbors will show the neighbors
            of node at the mouse cursor instead of those of the root node</li>
        </ul>
      </div>
    </item>
    <item type="enh">Improvements to the auto-update mechanism
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">The updater is a little more communicative in the
        unlikely event of a water landing or other mishaps.  Also, automatic checks for updates can
        be disabled.  Manual checks for updates can be triggered using the context menu of the
        network/document drop-down.</div>
    </item>
    <item type="new">New colormap &#8220;jet&#8221; (as in MATLAB),
      removed &#8220;focustop&#8221; and &#8220;focusbottom&#8221;</item>
    <item type="fix">Added work-around for binary sparse matrices with 1-based indices written by save_spato.m
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">All indices in XML data are 1-based, but indices in binary
        data (&#8220;blobs&#8221;) are 0-based.  If the weight matrix has no links to <nobr>node 0</nobr>
        but links to <nobr>node N</nobr>, all indices are adjusted by <nobr>&#8211;1</nobr>.</div>
    </item>
    <item type="fix">Maximum memory size now hardcoded to <nobr>1024 MB</nobr>
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">This should fix the fatal start-up problems in
        Windows.</div>
    </item>
    <item type="fix">Various other minor bug-fixes</item>
    <item type="new">Documents can be opened by dragging the .spato file into the application window
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">Of course, this item should read &#8220;data
        import still not available&#8221;, but we want to think positive...</div>
    </item>
    <item type="enh">Backbone is now called skeleton</item>
  </release>
  <release version="1.2.1_01" debug="alpha" date="20110227T130000">
    <item type="fix">Fixed invisibility of context menu items</item>
    <item type="enh">Previously opened documents are not automatically reloaded at startup
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">If any documents can be recovered, a button
        will be shown below the document list dropdown.</div></item>
    <item type="enh">Automatic estimation of Albers projection parameters</item>
  </release>
  <release version="1.2.1" debug="alpha" date="20110131T223000">
    <item type="new">Added option to show the network backbone<br />
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">Click the Backbone button in the upper left or press B
        to toggle display of the backbone.  All links of all trees are shown, color-coded by the number of
        trees they participate in (black indicating participation in all trees and lighter grays indicating
        participation in few trees).</div></item>
    <item type="enh">Screenshots now always render nodes using circles</item>
    <item type="enh">More secure self-update: now checking file authenticity with crypto-magic</item>
    <item type="enh">PDF fonts are loaded on application launch, reducing the time needed for producing the
      first screenshot</item>
    <item type="enh">Added splash screen on Windows to indicate that the application is launching</item>
    <item type="fix">Fixed crash on pressing snapshot album/series hot-keys when no snapshots are available
      in the displayed data</item>
    <item type="fix">Minor cosmetic changes to the user interface</item>
  </release>
  <release version="1.2.0_03" debug="alpha" date="20110102T193000">
    <item type="fix">Fixed wrong maximum-memory detection on 32-bit Windows</item>
    <item type="fix">Minor cleanups in the prelude</item>
  </release>
  <release version="1.2.0_02" debug="alpha" date="20110101T140000">
    <item type="fix">Changed colormap and radial scaling settings for each quantity are now remembered when
    revisiting that quantity.</item>
    <item type="enh">When displaying two-dimensional node-coloring data and holding down the Alt key, the
    displayed colors are determined by the node at the mouse cursor instead of the root node.</item>
  </release>
  <release version="1.2.0_01" debug="alpha" date="20110101T120001">
    <item type="enh">No more automatic fireworks at application launch<br />
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">Press Ctrl-Alt-F to start the show at any time, ESC to
      cancel.</div></item>
    <item type="new">New colormap:<br />
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0;"><img src="1.2.0_01__grayredblue.png" /></div></item>
  </release>
  <release version="1.2.0" debug="alpha" date="20110101T120000">
    <note>This is the first release using the new version numbering scheme</note>
    <item type="new">Automatic self-update mechanism (on Mac and Windows)</item>
    <item type="new">Full native platform integration on Mac OS X</item>
    <item type="new">Partial native platform integration on Windows</item>
    <item type="enh">Improved handling of uncompressed SPaTo documents<br />
      <div style="margin: 0.5em 0; font-size: 80%;">On Macs, the .spato folders are automatically registered
      as bundles and presented as single files to the user. On Windows and Linux, the "Open document" dialog
      now allows to select either the .spato folder or the document.xml inside the .spato folder.</div>
    </item>
    <item type="fix">Fixed not being able to change directory in the file chooser dialogs on Windows.</item>
  </release>
</release-notes>
